Prepare to crank those amps up to eleven.
This Is Spinal Tap is a comedy, music film directed by Rob Reiner.
"This Is Spinal Tap" shines a light on the self-contained universe of a metal band struggling to get back on the charts, including everything from its complicated history of ups and downs, gold albums, name changes and
undersold concert dates, along with the full host of requisite groupies, promoters, hangers-on and historians, sessions, release events and those special behind-the-scenes moments that keep it all real.
Nigel Tufnel, played by Christopher Guest.
David St. Hubbins, played by Michael McKean.
Derek Smalls, played by Harry Shearer.
Marty DiBergi, played by Rob Reiner.
Jeanine Pettibone, played by June Chadwick.
Tommy Pischedda, played by Bruno Kirby.
This Is Spinal Tap is a 1984 American mockumentary comedy film
directed by Rob Reiner in his feature directorial debut.
Christopher Guest, Michael McKean, and Harry Shearer play
members of the parody heavy metal band Spinal Tap.
Reiner plays Martin "Marty" Di Bergi, a documentary
filmmaker following the band's American tour.
The film satirizes the behavior and musical pretensions of rock bands and the hagiographic tendencies of rock documentaries such as The Song
Remains the Same (1976) and The Last Waltz (1978), similarly to what All You Need Is Cash (1978) by the Rutles did for the Beatles.
Reiner, Guest, McKean, and Shearer wrote the screenplay, though most of the
dialogue was improvised and dozens of hours were filmed.
This Is Spinal Tap was released by Embassy Pictures on March 2, 1984 to critical
acclaim, but found only modest commercial success in theaters.
Its later VHS release brought greater success and a cult following.
Credited with launching the mockumentary genre, it is also
notable as the origin of the phrase "up to eleven".
Deemed "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant" by the Library of
Congress, it was selected for preservation in the National Film Registry in 2002.
Reiner, Guest, McKean, and Shearer reprised their roles for the 2025 sequel Spinal Tap II: The End
Continues and the 2026 concert film Spinal Tap at Stonehenge: The Final Finale.
The film explores themes of rock star, groupie, parody, mockumentary, rock band.
The tone is lighthearted.